Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the CON42 Conference on
Observability twenty twenty-six.
Today, we are going to talk about
green dashboards and broken system.
Why do we still have a few broken
pieces here and there, incidents keep
happening, while your observability
system still shows everything as green?
I'm Umar Mokhtar.
I lead the product for
resilience testing at Harness.
I'm also a co-founder of Datamas
Chaos and OpenEBS, the popular
open source projects at CNCF.
I also co-founded a few companies,
Chaos Native, Mydata, and so on.
So what are we going to talk about
in the next few minutes here?
The premise is you have an
observability system, but you
have two different pictures.
Whereas the observability system
shows everything is green, but you see
the incidents still keep happening.
And these are not one or two incidents.
In large organizations, you see a lot
of system incidents keep happening your
users are affected, so on and so forth.
The purpose of observability
system is to get an idea of what's
going on in your environment
and then when the observability
system shows everything is green.
So why is this happening?
And that's exactly what we'll cover.
W-what is the gap and why is this
gap keep widening in the modern era,
especially in the agent-- AI agentic era?
And we'll also touch base on the
observability versus resilience testing.
And we'll also go through a little
bit of a case in point, a case
study as an example just for you
to understand a little bit more.
And then how do you
actually tackle this gap?
What is it that you can do?
And then how to treat this observability
and resilience in the new a-- agentic era.
So why now?
Just to recap, the point that we're
talking here is just because you're
seeing your systems as green on your
observability system, does it mean
that your systems are resilient?
May not be because this-- there are
incidents happening quite frequently
in your organization, right?
And this is important to realize this
gap, and the gap is actually widening.
The understanding that your systems
are stable is actually different
than the incident scenario.
Why is this happening now is there
are three accelerants, right?
The systems are becoming more
and more distributed, right?
There are too many dependencies, more
dynamic components are happening.
The releases with modern CI/CD
systems in place, releases
happening all the time, right?
The AI-assisted coding is actually helping
this gap widen even more and more because
you see releases happening multiple
times, tens of times within a day itself.
So when such is the release cadence,
you tend to see this gap more and more.
And then there is agents in the loop.
Agents are great.
They reason a lot, but there are some few
loopholes which I'm going to talk about.
So think about these three accelerants
as the reason the gap between your
system being shown as green versus
the incidents keep cropping up.
That's the gap, and these
are the accelerants, right?
So just because you have a clean
dashboard, that doesn't mean
that everything is green and
you can stay at peace, right?
Observability really is
about what's happening.
It does not show what
would happen in future.
There are so many silent parts your
observability may not cover, right?
That's exactly what we are
going to talk about, right?
So what your observability
dashboard cannot show.
Let's talk about few of them, right?
It never actually shows a
single point of failure.
It shows what's instrumented,
what's tested, right?
Whatever is not tested, it--
there could be a single point
of failure in some parts.
That will not be shown
in your dashboard, right?
And There are some timeouts or
retries that could trigger new
paths, and they were never triggered.
So all the time they were showing
green, and then whenever they're
triggered, your observability
system goes blank And degraded mode.
What if your system is in
degraded mode that was never seen?
That also your system
may not cover, right?
And a recovery plan, right?
How did your resilient-- how did
your observability dashboards go
when there was a DR testing happen?
Did you actually ever run a DR test?
If it was never run you would
never know how your dashboards
are going to look like.
These are some of the gaps.
Think about them as while you think
you may have a great set of dashboards,
these are some of the dashboards
you never actually touched upon.
They would become very handy if you
ever tested these four scenarios.
They would become very handy
when a real scenario happens.
A single point of failure triggers in a
lot of timeouts triggering, the system
goes into degraded mode or into DR, right?
At that time, your dashboards
are actually even more important
to see what's going on, right?
That's the gap that we
see in modern systems.
So what do you do about it, right?
So there is a four-step process
that I'm prescribing here to close
this loop or shorten the gap, right?
The first step is just go and
do the inventory of whatever was
tested paths versus non-tested path.
Just go and ask yourself a question:
Have we ever assumed about certain things
like what happens if this network fails?
Have you ever tested?
Do we know what happens?
What happens when a system goes down?
Do we know how the observability
looks like, or did we make an
assumption about how this works?
If we know the answer is
yes, then that's fine.
If the answer is no, that means you
don't know what's going to happen or you
never actually tested it, then make that
as a list into the inventory, right?
So go ahead and get as many
scenarios as possible about what
is untested, so on and so forth.
Then you take those scenarios and
then run controlled experiments
with less blast radius.
I'm going to talk about certain
tooling that is available to make these
controlled experiments run, right?
And then you get this results
back into your system and
create the dashboards for that.
All right?
So it's as simple as making the
inventory of the untested paths and
then go and create some controlled
experiments and then run them, see what's
missing in the dashboards, add them
back into your observability system.
Make this as a continuous effort.
It could be done quarterly or even
more often, so on and so forth.
So what this really means is that, you
will have more number of dashboards
that will become handy when the
system goes into red state, right?
Just because you have all the
system dashboards that are in
green, your observability system
may not be complete, right?
The system needs to have the
right dashboards when the
system goes into distress
So let's take an example how this happens
just to make the point more clear, right?
This is a pattern worth recognizing.
This is not a one-off story.
This happens all the time.
When you see the incidents happening,
observability system is the most
wanted trend, and then it will have
gaps coming up at that point, right?
So let's take a case in point.
Here, everything all the dashboards are
green, and then there is suddenly may
not be an incident, maybe a big alert
where the system goes into fallback path.
A third-party API stopped responding.
Now, the system is going into
a redundant path, and that
has never carried any traffic.
You actually never saw that
different path, and so you
never instrumented it, right?
So this actually, And one more thing
that happen can happen is, it's not an
alert yet, but the retries are happening
because this is a new path, and retry
storm actually turns the partial
outage into a full one within the next
thirty minutes or one hour, right?
While your observability system has never
captured whatever is happening in the
last thirty minutes to one hour, so it--
when it turns into a full outage, you
are really blank in debugging, right?
So how the how to fix this is
really not identify that failed
path and try that out in your lower
environment and have the dashboards
handy for that failed paths as well.
So when the real thing happens
in production, you're actually
capturing the real metrics on
your observability system, right?
That's the path that,
that we are recommending.
We also have another issue that
keeps coming up with respect
to the AI agents, right?
So this is a new failure shape.
The regular failures are all about, the,
the regular network failures, application
chaos, and so on and so forth, right?
The new failure shape is about
AI agents, and AI agents can
actually lie about the status.
So a green check on the health of an AI
agent may not be really green, right?
So the answer is wrong.
You may be checking is the AI agent
giving two hundred OK, but the back
end, the model that it is talking
to, it's actually slow but not down.
And the slow model is as
good as a bad model, right?
Bad scenario.
So a tool call that times out
silently but the agent keeps
sending two hundred OK, right?
So there are real failures
that are happening.
And there's a degraded step that could
actually hurt the system, but the AI agent
is showing the health as green, right?
So what I'm prescribing here is,
especially for the AI agent, you need
to create a new failure scenarios
where-- or introduce some latency
between the model endpoint and
the agent and see if the agent is
really showing okay or not, right?
An observability system that is
observing the agents need to capture
the real health of the agent in
these disturbed scenarios as well.
So this is the new issue that keeps
happening whenever there are a lot of
new AI agents that are deployed and
you're instrumenting your observability
systems for these AI agents.
So what is it that you can
do at a short time, right?
As a next step, right?
You can do all three of the
following one by one, right?
Go and take your most critical
list of services or service,
inventory that, right?
List every assumption that was
never observed in production.
Did we actually see this in production?
If not, that means it could happen.
Let me go and make an
inventory around it, right?
And then run the controlled experiments
and then see and make sure that you have
a dashboard capturing that path, right?
And then add new metrics,
so on and so forth, right?
And then also try to put the AI agentic
systems in a degraded mode and see
if your dashboards are showing up
proper health for your your AI agents.
So that's the kind of a new
premise that I want to set up.
And then I would like to take next few
minutes to go and show a system which
is capable of introducing controlled
experiments into your system in lower
environments as well as in production
and help you identify the risks.
Here we have Harness Resilience Testing.
It's a product on the Harness
platform that is capable of running
all kinds of resilience tests, chaos
experiments, load tests, and DR tests.
Chaos experiments is about giving
the idea of resilience when
small failures are introduced.
Load tests give you the idea of resilience
when systems are put under load.
And DR tests will give you the idea
of your system resilience when there
are major disasters, whether the
recovery plan works or not within the
required time and objective, right?
And it also gives an idea of the risks
that may be existing even without
running full list of experiment.
It's AI-powered.
The AI-assisted risk scanners can go
and look at your deployment metadata,
deployment logs, or it can browse the
inventory and then go and look at the
internal metadata, the configuration,
so on and so forth, events, runtime
logs, and see that, "Hey, there are
some risks that may be that may be
a real opportunity for a down-graded
system in the near future," right?
And it also actually gives
the idea of the risk.
It also helps the AI agents the
resilience test agent will help you
create chaos experiments and also run
which are the ones that need to be run
and then confirm the risks as well.
So you can also see there are some
recommendations that are driven by
AI assistance here, wherein you can
create the experiments automatically.
You don't need to spend a lot of time
to create these controlled experiments.
So overall, Resilience Testing is a
product on the Harness platform that
helps you Create controlled experiments,
run them, and see if the risks are real.
And during this experimentation process,
you can see if your instrumentation
on your observability system is
really working or not, right?
So just to close the loop, you have
an observability system that may
be showing everything is green.
You're going to take one further step
and see if there are some assumptions
that you made for the un-tested
scenarios, and make an inventory of them.
Take a tool like Harness Resilience
Testing, and go and create some
controlled experiments, run them, confirm
them, so you're reducing your risks.
Let's say, at, also at the same time,
you're preparing your observability
systems to have the dashboards for
these failure scenarios as well.
By the way the resilience testing
module has a full preplan.
It allows certain number of experiments
that can be run free forever on a
monthly basis, but all the capabilities
are available for you to make use of.
That's about today's keynote.
So don't assume that your systems
are all good, even though they
are showing all dashboards.
Go and prepare some dashboards for
the negative scenarios or doomsday
scenarios like DR plans as well.
I wish you good luck for the next set of
talks and have a fantastic conference.